<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!--
// Copyright (c) 1996-2007 The Regents of the University of California. All
// Rights Reserved. Permission to use, copy, modify, and distribute this
// software and its documentation without fee, and without a written
// agreement is hereby granted, provided that the above copyright notice
// and this paragraph appear in all copies.  This software program and
// documentation are copyrighted by The Regents of the University of
// California. The software program and documentation are supplied "AS
// IS", without any accompanying services from The Regents. The Regents
// does not warrant that the operation of the program will be
// uninterrupted or error-free. The end-user understands that the program
// was developed for research purposes and is advised not to rely
// exclusively on the program for any reason.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
// UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA BE LIABLE TO ANY PARTY FOR DIRECT, INDIRECT,
// SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, INCLUDING LOST PROFITS,
// ARISING OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE AND ITS DOCUMENTATION, EVEN IF
// THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA HAS BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
// SUCH DAMAGE. THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SPECIFICALLY DISCLAIMS ANY
// WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
// MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. THE SOFTWARE
// PROVIDED HEREUNDER IS ON AN "AS IS" BASIS, AND THE UNIVERSITY OF
// CALIFORNIA HAS NO OBLIGATIONS TO PROVIDE MAINTENANCE, SUPPORT,
// UPDATES, ENHANCEMENTS, OR MODIFICATIONS.
-->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../docbook-setup/docbookx/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<!--
  This is a translation of the version 11744 of the ArgoUML quickguide.
 -->

<book>
  <title>ArgoUML Quick Guide</title>
  <bookinfo>
    <subtitle>Get started with ArgoUML @VERSION@</subtitle>
    <authorgroup>
      <author><firstname>Kunle</firstname><surname>Odutola</surname></author>
      <author><firstname>Anthony</firstname><surname>Oguntimehin</surname></author>
      <author>
        <firstname>Linus</firstname>
        <surname>Tolke</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <firstname>Michiel</firstname>
        <surname>van der Wulp</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <copyright>
      <year>2001</year>
      <holder>Kunle Odutola</holder>
    </copyright>
    <copyright>
      <year>2004-2005</year>
      <holder>Michiel van der Wulp</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>
Este material se puede distribuir solamente conforme a los términos y a las condiciones dispuestos en la licencia abierta de publicación(Open Publication License), v1.0 o superior (la versión más actual está disponible en http://www.opencontent.org/openpub/) </para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>
  <chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Welcome to ArgoUML</title>
      <para> 
ArgoUML es un poderoso ambiente interactivo fácil de usar, de diseño gráfico de software que soporta el diseño, desarrollo y documentacion de aplicaciones de software orientadas a objeto.
</para>
      <para>Si está familiarizado con el conjunto de herramientas software como las de Ingeniería de Software Asistida por Computador (CASE, de sus siglás en inglés de Computer Aided Software Engineering) entonces de bería encontrar ArgoUML bastante familiar.
</para>
<para>
Los usuarios de ArgoUML son diseñadores de software y arquitectos, desarrolladores de software, analistas de negocio, analistas de sistema y otros profesionales envueltos en el analisis, diseño y desarrollo de aplicaciones de software. Sus características principales son:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Estándares abiertos: XMI, SVG and PGML
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
100% Independiente de la plataforma gracias al uso exclusivo de Java
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Fuente abierta, el cual permite su extensión o personalización.            
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Características cognitivas como: reflexión-en-acción, diseño oportunístico, comprensión y solución de problemas        
</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>

    <!--
    ===========================================================
    Chapter section template - copy for each major "topic" 
    discussed in this chapter
    ===========================================================
    -->
    <sect1>
      <title>About this guide...</title>
      <para> Esta guía - the ArgoUML Quick Guide    - se provee para que pueda 
      obtener y ejecutar lo más rápidamente posible ArgoUML.
      Provee instrucciones paso a paso para obtener, instalar y comenzar con ArgoUML,
       desarrollar tareas comunes, y aprender más de ArgoUML.
Si necesita mayor detalle por favor mire en el 
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/documentation/defaulthtml/manual/">
User Manual<!-- no fue traducido -->
</ulink>.
</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter id="installation">
    <title>Installing ArgoUML</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>System requirements</title>
      <para>Requerimientos mínimos de sistema
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Cualquier sistema operativo que soporte Java
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>10MB de espacio libre en el disco duro.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Mouse (u otro dispositivo similar) y teclado.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Java 2 JRE o JDK versión 1.4 o superior.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Installation options</title>
      <para>Ahora que Ud. tiene un computador en el que puede intalar y ejecutar ArgoUML efectivamente, debe decidir
      cual de las opciones de instalación disponibles es apropopiada para Ud. Puede escoger entre las siguientes opciones:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Java Web Start<!-- no lo traduje al español, ya que se conoce con ese nombre -->
</para>
            <para>
            Esta alternativa es buena para los usuarios ocasionales y los revisores. 
            Esta es la forma más fácil y rápida de para comenzar a utilizar ArgoUML.
			Requiere una conexion el sitio web de ArgoUML.
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Asegurese de tener
<ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/javawebstart/">
Java Web Start
</ulink>
instalado.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Siga el enlace que ejecuta ArgoUML desde el sitio web de ArgoUML.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
ArgoUML será descargado, guardado localmente en caché e iniciado.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
De ahí en adelante para comenzar, ArgoUML estará disponible tambien desde la consola
de Java Web Start (esto sin estar conectado a internet) y (si esta conectado)
en cada comienzo la versión será revisada a través del servidor web 
y se descargarán automaticamente sus actualizaciones.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Distibución binaria
</para>
            <para>
Esta es buena para los usuarios regulares y  garantiza que la versión 
no cambie durante el curso de su proyecto.
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Asegurese que tiene instalado Java 2 JRE.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Descargue la distribución binaria de ArgoUML desde el sitio web de ArgoUML.
</para>
                <para>
                
This could also include copying it to and from floppy disks or CD's
in order to get it to the computer if no network connection is
available.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Cree un directorio de instalación de ArgoUML.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Cambie el directorio actual al directorio de instalación de ArgoUML
y descomprima los archivos de ArgoUML en el directorio de instalación.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Comience por ejecutar el archivo <filename>argouml.jar</filename>, 
a través de un simple doble click en el archivo o ejecutando el siguiente comando:
                  <computeroutput>
java -jar argouml.jar
</computeroutput>
en la linea de mando, o via un archivo batch.
 <!-- la traducción normal sería archivo de procesamiento por lotes -->
</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </orderedlist>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Installing Auxiliary Modules</title>
      <para>
      La instalación normal de ArgoUML no soporta la generación de código en C++, php y C#.
      Para hacer esto posible, necesita descargar los 
      <literal>módulos auxiliares</literal> 
      desde la página de descarga del sitio web de ArgoUML.
</para>
      
      <para>
      Descomprima el archivo en el mismo directorio que desempaco 
      el mismo ArgoUML.
      
</para>
      
      <para>To 
      El resultado debe ser que el directorio que contiene el archivo
      <filename>argouml.jar</filename>, ahora tambien contenga un
      subdirectorio llamado <filename>ext</filename>, el cual contiene los archivos
      <filename>.jar</filename> para los lenguajes extra.
</para>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Command Line Options</title>
      
      <para>Cuando ejecute ArgoUML desde la linea de comando,
    entonces tiene varias posibilidades extra.
    Pruebe tipiando:</para>
      
      <para> <command>java -jar argouml.jar -help</command>
</para>
      
      <para>Ud. vería las instrucciones:</para>
      
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
Usage: [options] [project-file]
Options include:
  -help           display this information
  -big            use big fonts
  -huge           use huge fonts
  -nosplash       don't display logo at startup
  -noedem         don't report usage statistics
  -nopreload      don't preload common classes
  -norecentfile   don't reload last saved file
  -command <arg>  command to perform on startup
  -batch          don't start GUI
  -locale <arg>   set the locale (e.g. 'en_GB')
  -open <arg>     open given file on startup
  -print <arg>    print given file on startup (and exit)

You can also set java settings which influence the behaviour of ArgoUML:
  -Xms250M -Xmx500M  [makes ArgoUML reserve more memory for large projects]]]>
    </programlisting>
      
      <para>To be translated to Spanish:  A common problem is that the User Interface is shown in the wrong language. 
	  Below is an easy way to switch back to the English UI. 
	  Please beware: the language is in lowercase.
</para>
      
      <para> <command>java -jar argouml.jar -locale en</command>
</para>
      
      <para>To be translated to Spanish:  ArgoUML may be run without UI, in batch mode. 
	  Currently the possibilities are very limited. 
	  Below is an example (everything on 1 line!): 
	  It reads a "test.zargo" from my working directory, 
	  gets the diagram named "A", 
	  and writes a PNG graphical file for this diagram. 
	  Without the "-batch", 
	  ArgoUML would start up the UI after executing the commands. 
</para>
      
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: <command>java -jar argouml.jar -batch -command "org.argouml.uml.ui.ActionOpenProject=c:\Documents and Settings\Michiel\My Documents\test.zargo" -command org.argouml.ui.cmd.ActionGotoDiagram=A -command "org.argouml.uml.ui.ActionSaveGraphics=c:\Documents and Settings\Michiel\My Documents\test.PNG"</command>
</para>
      
    </sect1>
<sect1>
      
      <sect1info>
      
	<authorgroup>
	  <author>
	    <firstname>Ewan</firstname>
	    <othername>R.</othername>
	    <surname>Grantham</surname>
	  </author>
	</authorgroup>
	
      </sect1info>
      <title>Making .zargo-file clickable (on Windows) (Not yet translated to Spanish)</title>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
This works only if you have installed using the binary distribution.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
First, find a Zargo file, and right-click on it.
You should get the normal Windows menu, including an Open or Open With option.
At this point, give a description for the file like "ArgoUML Model", 
and tell Windows to use Notepad to open the file.
That's not what you want to do ultimately, but it does get Windows to
accept the .zargo extension as representing a valid file type.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
Now, open Windows Explorer and from the menu select View->Options 
(or on Windows XP: Tools->Folder Options...). 
You
should get a two (or more) tabbed dialog. Click the "File Types" dialog, and
then scroll through the list for the Description you gave - in the example
"ArgoUML Model". Click to select that file type, and then click the "Edit"
button.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
Now, click on the "Open" action and then the "Edit" button there. You will
then get a dialog that has a line for entering in the application action
which will have a line for using Notepad to open the file. Replace that line
with:
<command>
"C:\Program Files\Java\j2re1.4.0_01\bin\javaw.exe" -jar "c:\ArgoUML\argouml.jar" "%L"
</command>
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
Substitute your path to your <filename>javaw.exe</filename> and 
<filename>argouml.jar</filename> files if they are 
in a different location.
Click OK, then click OK, then click OK (three buttons on
three different levels of the dialog).
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: The %L in the above commandline is needed instead of %1 
because that is the way to
support filename extensions of more than 3 characters.
</para>
    </sect1>
    
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter id="running">
    <title>ArgoUML Principles (Not yet translated to Spanish)</title>
    <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
    When ArgoUML starts, then it shows an empty class diagram
    on which you can add various objects. ArgoUML works according the following
    principles:
</para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Project, Model and Diagram (Not yet translated to Spanish)</title>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      The file operations save and open handle one 
      <literal>project</literal> at a
      time. One <literal>project</literal> corresponds to a
      <literal>model</literal> plus diagram information, 
      i.e. everything you can edit within the ArgoUML window. 
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      The <literal>model</literal> may contain many
      objects (ModelElements) which
      form the complete UML description 
      of the system you are describing.
      All ModelElements might be present on a diagram, 
      but this is not required. 
      Hence, the <literal>model</literal> 
      that is stored in ArgoUML is
      independent of the contents of the diagrams. 
      This may be explained by the possibility 
      to generate programming code from the 
      <literal>model</literal> - you 
      do not need any diagrams for this.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      A ArgoUML <literal>project</literal> also contains 
      all diagram information, i.e.
      the shapes (presentation) used 
      to represent the various UML ModelElements, 
      their location, color, etc. 
      Some ModelElements appear on multiple diagrams, 
      some on one or none.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      Hence, saving and opening projects 
      retains all this information. 
      There is a way to only save the 
      <literal>model</literal> information
      though, which is by the menu 
      "Tools" -> "Export as XMI...". 
      This may be usefull e.g. 
      when generating programming code 
      with an external tool 
      that understands XMI.
</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Objects (Not yet translated to Spanish)</title>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      Select objects by left-clicking on them.
      The functionality of ArgoUML can be activated in the menu, 
      in toolbars,
      or in pop-up menus when right-clicking above an object.
      Many of these functions work on the selected objects.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      All diagrams have toolbars at the top which are used 
      to create objects on the diagram.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      Most objects can be added to a diagram and removed from a diagram without
      deleting it from the <literal>model</literal>! 
      Select an object on a diagram, and then the menu item 
      "Edit" -> "Remove from Diagram" clears the object from the diagram, 
      but the object remains intact in the model, 
      which may be seen in the explorer, 
      i.e. the tree structure at the left hand side.
      Once removed, and item can be added back to the diagram 
      (or any other diagram for that matter)
      by selecting it in the explorer 
      and selecting the item "Add to Diagram" 
      in the right-click pop-up menu.
</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Overview of the window (Not yet translated to Spanish)</title>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      The top of the window contains a menu bar with commands available.
      In the <literal>File</literal> menu you can store the project or 
      open another project instead.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      The upper left part of the ArgoUML window shows a tree model 
      of diagrams and objects. 
      This view can be adapted to your needs 
      by filtering the objects that are shown, 
      and the structure in which they are shown.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      The upper right part of ArgoUML shows the current diagram (one at a time).
      You can drag and drop the objects in the diagrams,
      and you can use the quick-links 
      that appear when hovering over a selected object 
      to create new objects connected to the
      already present objects.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      The lower right part contains various details of the currently selected 
      object: You select the object in one of the upper
      levels and choose what details you want to examine using the
      tabs.
</para>
      <para>To be translated to Spanish: 
      The lower left part contains a list of all ToDo items for this
      model.
</para>
    </section>
    
  </chapter>
  
</book>
